<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Justitiarius justificatus. = The iustice justified. Being an apologeticall remonstrance, / delivered to the honourable Commissioners, of the Great Seale, by George Wither Esquire, and occasioned by Sir Richard Onslow Knight, with some others, who moved to have him put out of the commission of the peace, in Surrey: in which private-defence, many things are expressed, verie pertinent to publike-consideration; and, top the vindication of the liberties of the subject, in generall, and of magistrates, in particular.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E506_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864929</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864929</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164286</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164286)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 80:E506[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Justitiarius justificatus. = The iustice justified. Being an apologeticall remonstrance, / delivered to the honourable Commissioners, of the Great Seale, by George Wither Esquire, and occasioned by Sir Richard Onslow Knight, with some others, who moved to have him put out of the commission of the peace, in Surrey: in which private-defence, many things are expressed, verie pertinent to publike-consideration; and, top the vindication of the liberties of the subject, in generall, and of magistrates, in particular.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 13th 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Libel and slander --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:164286:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Juſtitiarius juſtificatus.</hi> The Iuſtice juſtified.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being, an <hi>Apologeticall Remonſtrance,</hi> delivered to the Honourable Commiſſioners, of the Great Seale, by <hi>George Wither</hi> Eſquire; and occaſioned by Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow</hi> Knight, with ſome others, who moved to have him put out of the <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace,</hi> in <hi>Surrey:</hi> In which private-Defence, many things are expreſſed, verie pertinent to publike-conſideration; and, to the vindication of the Liberties of the <hi>Subject,</hi> in generall, and of Magiſtrates, in particular.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HOnourable Lords, and Gentlemen,</hi> to whoſe cuſtodie and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, the great <hi>Seal</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> is committed; ſuffer, I beſeech you, with patience, that, an humble Servant to the <hi>Muſes,</hi> may, for a few minutes, make his defence before you, againſt thoſe who have lately abuſed both <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> by an impertinent Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. In the nobleſt <hi>Ages,</hi> and moſt glorious <hi>Common-Wealths,</hi> they, who were reputed Retainers to <hi>Apollo,</hi> were ever heard (in making their defences) with good reſpect; yea, even in thoſe times and places, wherin ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſitie, &amp; civilitie, were leaſt regarded, men had ſo much wit, that though they ſecretly hated them, yet, for their owne honour, they uſually kept fair quarter, with that <hi>Generation:</hi> and, it is a ſymptome of much ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when men do needleſſely ingage themſelves by provoking others to the hazzarding of their credit, and quiet. Miſtake me not, I pray you, as if I thus began, my Apologie, to intimate ſome ſuch imprudencie in you, my <hi>moſt honourable Judges;</hi> for, I unfainedly profeſſe, that, I neither have any purpoſe, nor know any juſt cauſe, ſo to doe: but, have made this preamble, only, to hint unto thoſe againſt whom I plead, what danger they might have incurred, if I had been one of thoſe <hi>Wits,</hi> whoſe <hi>Iambicks,</hi> can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> make men their owne executioners; or, if I ſhould have raged-out, an <hi>Invective,</hi> in bluſtring <hi>Numbers,</hi> inſtead of this <hi>Apologie,</hi> which I now, calmely, deliver in <hi>Proſe.</hi> But, to the matter.</p>
            <p>It was my ill fortune (without my own ſeeking, deſire, or fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, untill it was done) to be made a <hi>Commiſſioner for the Peace</hi> and <hi>Goale-Delivery</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> ſince the beginning of this <hi>war;</hi> and, I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the troubles which I might thereby bring upon my ſelf, by reaſon of the factiouſneſſe and malignancie of theſe times (and the ſmall eſtate, which the furie of the <hi>Common-enemy</hi> had left me) thought it good diſcretion not to accept thereof; and was ſo reſolved, untill that reſolution was unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:164286:2"/>changed by the perſwaſion of Friends, who made me believe, that God, by my <hi>unſought-for admittance,</hi> evidenced his <hi>calling</hi> of me, to ſerve <hi>him</hi> and my <hi>Countrey,</hi> in her great neceſſities; and that, <hi>honeſty</hi> and <hi>good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> joyned with an ordinarie underſtanding, might make me as ſervicecable, as ſome other, who had abler <hi>Faculties,</hi> and larger <hi>Eſtates.</hi> Thereupon, I accepted thereof, becauſe my education in the <hi>Vniverſity</hi> and <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> made me, as I thought, no leſſe capable of that <hi>Office</hi> then ſome other of my <hi>Fellow-Commiſſioners;</hi> and, becauſe, alſo, my knowne converſation, my faſhion of living, &amp; my being ever ſince my youth, an acceptable companion to many <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>honourable perſons,</hi> would render me (as I conceived) a <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> without contempt; though moſt part of my eſtate was taken away: which, I thank God, I have hitherto been, except among ſome of thoſe, <hi>creatures without underſtanding,</hi> who uſually value themſelves, and others, according to their <hi>Trappings:</hi> But, I chiefly accepted thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſaw many poore ſoules grievouſly oppreſſed by their <hi>tyrannous neighbours,</hi> and hoped, God would by that Authoritie, enable me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſome of them.</p>
            <p>But, inſtead of what I then hoped, that, which I feared not, came to paſſe: For, Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow,</hi> and ſome other of his <hi>Friends</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Surrey,</hi> have as it ſeems found it pertinent to the eſtabling of their <hi>Deſigns</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> there, that I ſhould be thruſt out of the <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace,</hi> as I have been, out of ſome Committees, and out of my habitation, for no other cauſes, but ſuch as are concealed in the breaſt of the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard;</hi> who, having got (as it were) the Supremacie over all Cauſes, and all Perſons <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> and <hi>Civill,</hi> within his Dominions, diſpoſeth of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> preferreth <hi>Deputie-Lievtenants,</hi> maketh and unmaketh <hi>Juſtices</hi> of the <hi>Peace, Committee-men, Colonells,</hi> and all other inferiour <hi>Militarie Officers, Marſhalls, Treaſurers,</hi> and <hi>Collectors,</hi> as hee pleaſeth; yea, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and diſ-favours, impoſeth and taketh off, impriſons and ſets at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, builds up and puls downe, armeth and diſ-armeth, ordreth and diſ-ordreth, according to his diſcretion, with little or no contradiction. And that his pleaſure may be fulfilled in all things, your Honours (as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) have been lately ſollicited, by him, to caſhiere me from the <hi>Bench.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At firſt hearing thereof, I ſleighted it as a thing not worthy my regard; and within my ſelfe, laughed to ſcorne the poore vanitie of mine <hi>Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> who thinks all my honour lyes, as his doth, about <hi>Guildford,</hi> and the Weſt-Diviſion of <hi>Surrey;</hi> or, that, my contentment conſiſteth in having authoritie and power over others, upon ſuch tearmes, and to ſuch frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ends, as moſt men deſire, and aſſume it for: and, thereupon, I thought to paſſe it over with perpetuall neglect. But, having better conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thereof, and what encouragement it might give mine enemies, to improve their malice, in matters of more concernment, to my ſelfe, and perhaps, to the diſheartening, and enſlaving of others, by his prevailing againſt mee; I ſaw it verie neceſſarie, to take ſpeedy notice of the wrong done: not only, leſt my Oppreſſours ſhould be encouraged to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe me the more; but, leſt they might, alſo, fooliſhly conceive, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:164286:2"/>I <hi>do not,</hi> therefore I <hi>could not</hi> vindicate my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Vpon this conſideration, I have humbly preſumed to make an <hi>Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Remonſtrance</hi> againſt them and their proceedings, who have appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before you, to do me ſuch an affront, as had been too much, when <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> raigned; and is therefore, much leſſe to be endured now the <hi>Sword</hi> is drawne for the <hi>Rights,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> of a <hi>Free People.</hi> And, though the <hi>honour</hi> which I care for, and chiefly aime at, is not ſuch as may be added, unto me, or taken from me, at other mens diſcretions; yet (I being a little ſenſible of that <hi>Diſgrace</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> which men of my conſtitution and frailtie are uſually affected withall) have a mind to prevent the <hi>ſcorne of Fooles,</hi> if I may, by preſerving my credit (through your favour and juſtice) in keeping that authoritie, which my <hi>Adverſaries</hi> endeavour to take from me; or, elſe, by making them and their Favourers to ſee, that, I know how to honour my ſelfe, twice as much, another way; and, how to hew <hi>Staires,</hi> out of their <hi>Affronts,</hi> whereby I may aſcend <hi>higheſt,</hi> when they think they have brought me to the <hi>loweſt condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not tell your Honours, how great a diſgrace it is thought, to be put out of that <hi>Commiſſion:</hi> For, you verie well know, it is not uſually permitted, ſave for verie groſſe and apparant miſdemeanours; and never upon any clandeſtine, or ſleight informations; except, <hi>Will</hi> ſtood for <hi>Law,</hi> and when they kept the <hi>Seale,</hi> who did arbitrarily put men in, and out, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they were ſwayed by their own, or by other mens <hi>corruptions:</hi> of which, I am not jealous at this time; becauſe, I have good hopes of your <hi>Equitie,</hi> many evidences of mine owne <hi>Integritie,</hi> and, no feare of my greateſt <hi>Enemies;</hi> except it be, that, they will not deſiſt from cauſeleſly, and fooliſhly troubling and provoking me, till they compell mee to make all the Kingdome know them by <hi>name,</hi> and underſtand their purpoſes, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well as I do. I cannot, therefore, beleeve that perſons ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſo wiſe as your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> will permit me to be (as if were) kic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked off like a foot-ball without hearing; I, having been once reputed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſupply the room of a <hi>Iudge upon Record;</hi> ſeeing, if ſuch an indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhould be offered, no man of merit, or of a right underſtanding, would adventure himſelfe upon ſuch a tottering ſeat as the <hi>Seſſions-Bench;</hi> or, be much incouraged to relieve, and deliver the oppreſſed, from their injurious and tyrannous neighbours; leſt, when he was doing his dutie, and thought himſelfe ſufficiently authorized to be a comfort to others, he might be ſecretly diſabled, from ſecuring his own perſon, from diſgrace and ruine.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>my Lords,</hi> it honeſt men ſhall be (as it were) purpoſely ſet up, to be pulled ſuddenly downe againe, to their diſparagement, <hi>without hearing;</hi> upon the motion of an <hi>Adverſarie;</hi> yea, and when their converſations and deportments (who are traduced, or ſollicited againſt) have been ſuch, that they dare ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e and challenge triall, as I do: Or, if the Office of a <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> bee but a complement of reſpect, which you, of higher place, ſhall think fit to ſhew us; a <hi>thing</hi> to be played withall; or, an <hi>Ornament</hi> to be put upon us, and torne from us againe, at pleaſure, according to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and changeable inclinations of others; let them take it, who are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164286:3"/>with ſuch toies; yea, let the greateſt fools of the Kingdom monopolize it to themſelves: for, I ſhall be ſo far from deſiring to be continued in it, on thoſe tearmes, that, I ſhall ſcorn it, as fitting for none, but <hi>ſneaking, baffel'd,</hi> and <hi>poore-ſpirited Fellowes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, the Dignitie of that <hi>Truſt</hi> and employment, is indeed ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the due execution thereof is of ſo much conſequence, that it ought to be preſerved from contempt, by being conferred on perſons deliberately choſen, and eminent where they live, for their underſtanding and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, having, alſo, eſtates competently ſufficient, to bear the charge of their Magiſtracie, and to be anſwerable for their over-ſights: And, when ſuch are once authorized, it is fitting that their reputation ſhould be preſerved, ſo long as they continue in their integritie, &amp; that they ſtand not in hazard of a diſgraceful removal, by the diſ-favour, or ſecret ſupplantings of other men, ſo long as they are able and willing to ſerve their Countrey. For to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that, or any other <hi>Office of Judicature</hi> (for an uncertaine terme) <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti bene placito,</hi> expreſſively or implicitely intended, rather than with this clauſe, <hi>Quàm diu ſe bene geſſerit,</hi> was the practice of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> who intended, thereby, to make their <hi>Officers</hi> the more ſerviceable to their <hi>Arbitrarie Deſignes;</hi> and, therfore, it ought not to be endured in a free and well-governed <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> eſpecially, in a time when Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is intended, and by us, who have had experience often, and lately, to our coſt and ſmart, that, when men were conſcionable of their duties, and active in the execution of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> according to the letter and equitie of the Lawes, (without fear or reſpect of perſons) it was uſuall to remove them with diſgrace; and to ſupply their places, with ſuch as would be conformable to the corrupt <hi>will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of tyrannous <hi>Princes,</hi> and their Paraſiticall <hi>Favourites</hi> and <hi>Counſellours,</hi> to the publike detriment, and diſhonour. And, doubtleſſe, when a man (which is my caſe) who never ſought for it, or deſired it, ſhall be called to an <hi>Office of truſt,</hi> and made to pay great fees for being admitted, and for accepting to do the publike ſervice, to his own trouble, and further coſt, without profit; if then, and, even, after he hath faithfully executed the ſame (to the accumulating of hatred to himſelfe, for doing juſtice) he ſhall be diſgracefully <hi>caſt out,</hi> before <hi>hearing,</hi> or any <hi>Cauſe ſhowne,</hi> be left a caſhiered <hi>Officer</hi> upon record; it is an injurie juſtly to be complained of, and fit to be remedied, and provided againſt.</p>
            <p>I cannot imagine, that, the Gentlemen who took pains to appear, and ſollicite your Honours againſt mee, brought any conſiderable argument to prove reaſonable that which they deſired; or, that the diſplacing of me, was any thing pertinent to the well-governing of Surrey; nor have I yet any certaintie of what they alleaged, becauſe nothing is upon record. But, what moved ſome of them againſt mee, I do verie well know; yea, and why they are ſo deſirous to be rid of my fellowſhip, and neighbourhood in Surrey: which, I will forbear now to mention; and, that I may be the more ſure to take off all thoſe juſt exceptions, which, in my underſtanding, may ſeem helpfull to accompliſh their purpoſe, I will ſuppoſe objections, and make diſtinct anſwers unto them, for my vindication.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:164286:3"/>
            <p>All Objections, which I think can juſtly be made againſt thee, or any other, to render him uncapable or unworthy to be continued a <hi>Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Peace,</hi> muſt either concern his <hi>manners,</hi> his <hi>Religion,</hi> his <hi>knowledge</hi> or <hi>judgement,</hi> his <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> to Supreme Authoritie, his <hi>uprightneſſe</hi> in the execution of his <hi>Office,</hi> or the <hi>Competencie of his eſtate;</hi> and I will make it apparent, that in all theſe reſpects, I am as little to be excepted againſt, as ſome of thoſe, who are, yet, to be continued in <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> with their good liking, who have excepted againſt me: yea, I preſume I ſhall approve my ſelf free from any juſt exception, (notwithſtanding the <hi>Statute</hi>) the <hi>times,</hi> and the preſent condition of this <hi>Realme,</hi> being rightly conſidered.</p>
            <p>As touching my <hi>manners, my life, and converſation,</hi> (though I am a great ſinner to God) I thinke no man hath impudence enough to lay any thing to my charge; no, not Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow,</hi> who I am confident would not ſpare to diſcover any thing, whereby he might ſafely, and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, diſparage and undo me; and, therefore, I will apologize for my ſelfe no further in that reſpect, untill he, or ſome other, ſhall accuſe me. My <hi>Religion</hi> teacheth me to renounce the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacie, and, that is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion enough, to keep mee ſtill in the <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace,</hi> though I profeſſed no more; therefore, I ſhall not need to <hi>catechize</hi> my ſelfe, or to make a larger <hi>Confeſſion of my faith,</hi> upon this <hi>Occaſion.</hi> My <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>judgement,</hi> hath, hitherto, been as ſeldom, and as little queſtioned as any of my neighbours: and, if it be but ſufficient (as I hope it is) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me to ſpeake, and diſcharge my dutie, without the controule or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of my <hi>Clerk,</hi> I am perſwaded, it is more ſufficiencie, then all my <hi>Fellow-Juſtices,</hi> throughout this Kingdome, may truly boaſt of. My <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> to the <hi>State,</hi> is ſo over-much evidenced to my dammage at this preſent, and ſo generally knowne, by my expreſſions and ſufferings, heretofore, as well as by my great loſſes, disburſements, endeavours, and the hazarding of my life, in this War, that, moſt men of qualitie in theſe parts, do repute mee a man, to be unqueſtionably confided in, by the <hi>State;</hi> and in my conſcience, if it had been otherwiſe, ſome who are now mine <hi>Eenemies,</hi> would have been my verie <hi>good Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the execution of my <hi>Office,</hi> I have neither <hi>denyed, delayed,</hi> or <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Iuſtice,</hi> ſince my admiſſion thereunto; nor put anie man to ſo much coſt for it, as the expence of one <hi>Clerks-Fee;</hi> becauſe, I have hitherto diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched all buſineſſes with my one hand, and am loth to put any man to more charge then need requires. I confeſſe, I have not acted ſo much in the duties of that place, as the many diſorders, and the prophaneneſſe of many among us requires; by reaſon, that, ſome of thoſe, who now labour to put me out of the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> have done what in them lies to drive me out of the <hi>County</hi> alſo, and have made my reſidence, there, to be of late verie ſeldome and uncertain: yea, and as far as they dared, they have done me diſreſpects, and diſcourteſies (if I may terme them no worſe) in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of all my <hi>Warrants,</hi> which have come to their knowledge; and laboured to make me vile, and contemptible, among my neighbours, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:164286:4"/>
            <p>For, when I had ſent my <hi>Warrant</hi> for a dangerous Knave and a Whore, who had travelled together out of Surrey, into the Kings Quarters (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, imployed to conveigh intelligence) and, who lived in manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, at their returne; theſe (refuſing contemptuouſly to be obedient to my <hi>Authority</hi>) were countenanced therein, to my diſgrace; and to the incouragement of ſuch varlets, and baſe people, in their contempts, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe. And, whereas I had lately committed two ſuſpitious fellowes, upon very ſtrong probabilities of horſe-ſtealing, and had ſignified what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence I had of their being dangerous perſons, and not fit to be bailed, but by very good ſureties; ſome of theſe <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> having the Priſoners carried afterwards before them, by the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> (who was to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed them immediately to the Goale, according to his duty, and my Warrant) the matter was (as it ſeemeth) ſo ſleighted, that the ſaid Conſtable ſuffered one of them, negligently, or wilfully, to eſcape that night: and, for the other, a few weeks after, mean Baile was taken, by one, or moe of the ſaid Gentlemen; not without ſcandalous intimations (as I have heard) that the poore fellow was not, by me, proceeded againſt, ſo much for being a ſuſpitious perſon, as for that I thought thereby to get his horſe; he being apprehended, in a Mannour where the Felons goods belong unto me: of which intimation, if any of them were guilty, it implies an inveterate malice, much to be taken heed of: and if my reputation ſtood in need to be cleared from ſuch a baſe aſperſion, it will be vindicated at the next Goale-deliverie in Surrey: For, the ſame partie whom they ſo bailed, as a man whom I ſuſpected, not without evident cauſe, hath (ſince he was let forth upon Baile) committed divers other Felonies; and, is now, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehended, and, a priſoner againe, by my diligence.</p>
            <p>Now, if the exception made againſt me, be grounded upon that obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete <hi>Statute</hi> which requires everie <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> to have Land of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, of ſuch, or ſuch an yearly value, in the County (which, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is all that can be reaſonably objected to have me put out of Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) then, there is a coulerable exception againſt me: For, indeed, I have no inheritance there, but onely a hundred pounds per annum for a terme to come, and ſome poſſibilities of more hereafter. And, if I ſhall be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for that only; then, my removall is without any fault of mine: For, it is not meerly my fault, (and I think your Honours will believe it) that I have not land enough to be a <hi>Iuſtice of Peace,</hi> in everie County of the Kingdome: nor doth, indeed, either the practiſe, or conſtitution of the times require the ſtrict obſervance of that <hi>Statue,</hi> but permits, and neceſſitates a diſpenſation thereof: And, ſome, even in that <hi>County,</hi> who have not eſtates there anſwerable to the Letter of the <hi>Law,</hi> are, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, kept ſtill in <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> and were firſt admitted (as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) by means of ſome, or one of thoſe, who ſeek to have mee caſt out, for the ſame inconſiderable defect. Amongſt which perſons, there are two verie obſerveable; one of them (who hath but a little plot of Oſiers in that Countie) is ſo well befriended at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that (as I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) he had lately a <hi>Warrant for Veniſen</hi> out the walled park near King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164286:4"/>under the Kings own hand: the other, who, ſeems to be either <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> or <hi>Sollicitor Generall</hi> for <hi>Delinquents,</hi> at <hi>Kingſton-Committee,</hi> hath no more but a poore Potters cottage near Chertſey in that Countie, of about eight pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> There, is otherwhile, as much need of <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>honeſty,</hi> in the execution of that <hi>Office,</hi> as of a <hi>Landed-man.</hi> Men of <hi>large fortunes,</hi> and <hi>little conſcience,</hi> have ſo long ingroſſed places of <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi> and made ſuch uſe of <hi>Magiſtracie,</hi> for private and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ends, that, they have deſtroyed our <hi>Peace,</hi> and indangered all our <hi>Freedomes:</hi> and, therefore, it is now requiſite (and, God, in juſtice, will ſo have it) that, the ſtout, faithfull, and prudent <hi>Citizens,</hi> and the men of <hi>midling-Fortunes,</hi> who were heretofore ſcorned and oppreſſed, ſhould be called into <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>imployment,</hi> that (if it be poſſible) their courage, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, pietie, and integritie, might help our honourable <hi>Senators,</hi> to redeeme us from thoſe miſeries, and ſlaveries, into which the <hi>Canibals</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> and the <hi>Sagamores</hi> of the <hi>Countrey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> have by their pride, and perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, lately brought us. And, doubtleſſe, though this temporarie cauſe of diſpenſing with the <hi>Statute</hi> were removed, it were no intrenchment upon the true intent and equity of the <hi>Law (according to which your Court ought to judge</hi>) if a <hi>Iuſtice of Peace</hi> be continued, who hath a perſonall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſufficient to keep his Authority from contempt; and, to inable the diſcharge of his dutie: eſpecially, if the <hi>Kingdome</hi> be ſo much indebted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him (as it is now to me, even in the ſame Countie where I am a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner</hi>) that, it may ſuffice to repaire, all publike, and private dammages alſo, which may be ſuſtained by the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> Imprudence, neglect, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Sure I am, if none ſhould be <hi>Commiſſioners of the Peace,</hi> in ſome Counties, as our affaires now ſtand, but great <hi>Landlords;</hi> there would be little hope of equity, in many places.</p>
            <p>Having thus pleaded to every exception, which may be colourably made againſt me; I could ſay ſomwhat els, lying now at my torgues end, which if it were plainly expreſſed, and could be as well proved to others, as it is manifeſt to my ſelfe, would, perhaps, both continue me in the <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace,</hi> and make me of the <hi>Quorum</hi> alſo, if it were uttered in a good houre: But, becauſe good dayes, and houres, are verie rare and uncertaine with me; and, leſt a worſe thing may befall me, than putting out of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> (if it be ill timed) I will ſilence my preſent thoughts, for ever; or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I ſee ſuch a day, as may give them a happie birth, without hazard: and, I will now expreſſe ſomewhat, to take away that rigid opinion of me, which may, perhaps, be entertained, by reaſon, ſo many Gentlemen of <hi>Surrey</hi> have appeared with Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow,</hi> to ſollicite your Honours to put me out of Commiſſion. For, doubtles, it could not but make the whole <hi>Court,</hi> and all there preſent, who knew me not, to conceive unworthily of me; and therefore, though not for mine owne ſake, yet for the ſake of that which God hath heretofore enabled mee to expreſſe, concerning this <hi>Nation,</hi> and the judgements now upon us (which may, elſe, be made the leſſe regarded, and the leſſe effectuall to thoſe who read me) it ſeems neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, that I ſhould apologize, a little, to that purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:164286:5"/>
            <p>If I did not know, that to be an honeſt man, and a profeſt enemy to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and oppreſſions, were enough to make me hated and perſecuted of ſome men; or, if experience had not acquainted me, how cunningly ſome can draw in others, to make their preſence a countenance to their deſignes, who know not why they are called (as, by their own confeſſion to me, it fared with ſome who accompanied Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow</hi> to your Honours) I ſhould have much wondred, that, ſo many Gentlemen ſhould have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in ſo diſcourteous an office, conſidering, moſt of them have ſeemed to reſpect me, and are men whom I love and honour; and, conſidering alſo, how civilly I have ever behaved my ſelfe toward them, and all other of that <hi>Countie,</hi> not withſtanding many provocations to the contrarie.</p>
            <p>For, I ſolemnly proteſt before God, that, to my remembrance, I do not know any perſon in <hi>Surrey,</hi> with whom I had any quarrell, or unkind conteſtation, before this <hi>War,</hi> or ſince it began, but, with reſpects, meerly to the Publike Cauſe; neither any one, whom I have, wittingly, wronged ſo much, in <hi>deed</hi> or <hi>word,</hi> but, that, one penny will make ſatisfaction, for the whole injurie, ſeven-fold. Nay, I have not done to any one of thoſe <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> ſo much as a ſeeming injurie, or <hi>diſ-reſpect,</hi> except, it ſeemeth a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect, to have refuſed to joyne with ſome of them in the erecting of Alc-houſes, or in ſuch like concurrences, which I thought unfitting to be aſſented unto: Or, except it may ſeeme a <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> to Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Onſlow,</hi> that I lately ſet at libertie a poore man, whom (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) hee had arbitrarily, and wrongfully committed, without cauſe ſhewne, to the infringement of the juſt <hi>Freedomes</hi> of the people, and the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Land: Or, except he thinks it a <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> unto him (as I have heard he takes it to be, with an imputation of ingratitude unto mee) that, I will not acknowledge my ſelfe to have been made <hi>Captaine</hi> of the Horſe firſt raiſed in <hi>Surrey,</hi> for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> meerly, by his friendſhip; whereas, he, and the Countie knowes, I was made choyce of, by the <hi>Well-affected,</hi> before he had any thought of me to that purpoſe; yea, and in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to his election: For (till he ſaw it would be in vain) hee laboured to bring in the ſon in Law of Mr. <hi>Muſchamp,</hi> then, reputed a violent <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant;</hi> and the Gentleman whom hee would have made Captaine, was not, at that time, barely ſuſpected, but ſo really a <hi>Malignant,</hi> that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, ſoone after, a <hi>Commander</hi> for the <hi>King;</hi> where (I verily beleeve) hee did him worſe ſervice, than hee might have done, had hee commanded thoſe Horſe in <hi>Surrey.</hi> Or, except it ſeemeth a <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> to Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> that I would not re-admit upon his Letter, (and upon his engagement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me for him) the naturall ſon of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Muſcamp,</hi> to be Cornet of my Troop; out of which place (the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard</hi> having preferred him thereto) I caſhiered him, becauſe hee behaved himſelfe mutinouſly, and ſought to allure away my Troopers, and my <hi>Lievtenant</hi> to ſerve the <hi>King;</hi> unto whom the ſaid <hi>Cornet</hi> went, ſhortly after, and was made a <hi>Captain</hi> alſo. My <hi>Lievtenant,</hi> being likewiſe of Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow's</hi> owne choice, I was forced to caſhiere, as well becauſe he leaned the ſame way, as for other miſdemeanours. Or, except it ſeems a <hi>diſ-reſpect,</hi> to Sir <hi>Richard,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:164286:5"/>that, before his conſent thereunto, I was (without my ſeeking or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, untill it was determined) freely, and unanimouſly nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated for <hi>Colonell,</hi> by the Committee of the <hi>Militia</hi> for <hi>Surrey,</hi> (being a very full Committee ſitting at <hi>Kingſton</hi>) and was (by the ſame Committee) Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 7. 1644. ordered to take charge of all Forces, then raiſed, and to be raiſed, in the Eaſt, and middle Diviſions of <hi>Surrey;</hi> and, that, I preſumed to accept therof, without Sir <hi>Richard Onſlowes</hi> conſent; who, indeed, was much out of patitience there with, and could never after be at quiet, untill he had contrived the new modelling of the <hi>Militia,</hi> there, according to his own fancie; For, thereupon he procured the reducement therof under the <hi>Lievtenancie</hi> again, by which <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or, except it ſeeme a <hi>diſ-reſpect,</hi> unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> that when he offered to be <hi>Commander in chief,</hi> over the whole <hi>Militia</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> and to make mee his <hi>Lievtenant-Colonell,</hi> I refuſed the ſame, thinking it no diſcretion to quit a ſuperiour, for an inferiour <hi>Command;</hi> or, to hazard the being twice deceived, by one man; or, to ſubject my ſelf, to him, who (I thought) regarded neither my profit, nor my credit, nor my life: and, I partly refuſed it, becauſe I was loath to be ſharer with him in the honour gotten (if I may ſo call it) at the ſiege of <hi>Baſing;</hi> which was famous, at that time, through the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Or, except it ſeem a <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> unto him, that I ſeldome concurred with him, in his deſignes; eſpecially, in his oppoſition to the Aſſociation; in his arming Malignants, and others promiſcuouſly; and, in his putting the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> into thoſe poſtures, and to thoſe exceſſive-impertinent charges, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which, in my judgment, were more likelie (by weakening, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contening the people) to indanger, then to ſecure, thoſe parts. Or, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he conceive it a <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> unto him, that, when in my <hi>Se-Defendendo,</hi> I publikely vindicated my ſelfe, from being anie way blameable, that, <hi>Farn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham-Caſtle</hi> (whereof I had command at the beginning of this <hi>warre</hi>) was left imprudently (if not treacherouſly) to the <hi>Enemy;</hi> and ſo clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſelfe, that, I thereby gave thoſe who were unſatisfied, occaſion to ſeek further, and lay the fault where it was. Or, except it ſeem a diſ-reſpect to Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow,</hi> that I ſhould ſay, I thought, his procuring me to be put into the fore-ſaid <hi>Caſtle,</hi> was not for that end which he firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: For, when I conſider the ſeries, and concatenation of his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in <hi>Surrey,</hi> and his continuing-endeavours, from time, to time, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, with reference to that <hi>Caſtle,</hi> (with the manifold charges, diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, and diviſions, which have been occaſioned, by his reſtleſſe ſeeking to accommpliſh ſome ſecret deſigne of his own, which, I conceive he hath, or hath had, upon that <hi>Place</hi>) I am ſtill, ſo perſwaded, my thoughts have therein done him no wrong; that, I profeſſe againe, I do verily believe, he hath aimed at ſome eſtabliſhment there, for his own advantage, ever ſince the warre began: and, that he hath thereby occaſioned moſt of the miſeries which have waſted Hampſhire, and Surrey; and, becauſe this beleefe ſhall not appeare to bee without a <hi>Foundation,</hi> I will, out of a long <hi>chaine</hi> of <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> linked into each other, preſent you with a few.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why I do beleeve, that hee, the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> occaſioned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164286:6"/>much of the ſpoyle made in <hi>Hamp-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Surrey;</hi> is, for that, it ſeemeth unto me, to be chiefly (if not altogether) his fault, that a ſtrong <hi>Garriſon</hi> was not eſtabliſhed at <hi>Farnham,</hi> when the command thereof was firſt given unto me: For, had that <hi>Southerne paſſage</hi> to <hi>London</hi> been ſtrongly guarded, by well fortifying of <hi>Farnham,</hi> for the preſent, and by removing the <hi>Garriſon</hi> afterward to <hi>Baſing</hi> (according to my deſigne then propoſed) wee ſhould have ſo comforted, and encreaſed, the Well-affected; and ſo diſcouraged, and ſuppreſſed Malignants, that, many of thoſe occaſions would have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, which drew both <hi>Parties,</hi> ſo often, that way, to the impoveriſhing, and diſcontenting of thoſe <hi>Counties;</hi> yea, and a little charge (in reſpect of what was afterward neceſſitated) would, at firſt, have kept out the floud, which made the firſt breach, and ſpoyl; and which, being once made, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince be ſtopped ſo ſtrongly up, but that everie little Torrent broke in upon us; to the encreaſing, or prolonging, of our afflictions.</p>
            <p>The reaſons, why I beleeve it his fault, that, for preventing theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, a ſtrong <hi>Garriſon</hi> was not timely compleated at <hi>Farnham,</hi> are theſe: Vpon due examination, of his beginning and his proceedings, I could perceive no aſſurance, that he intended to fortifie it; unles it might be for ſuch ends as he ſecretly purpoſed: For, the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> wherby I was made <hi>Governor</hi> (thogh procured, by Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> in my <hi>Name,</hi> and delivered to me) was ſo drawn up, that, what I ſeemed to be, I was not. He himſelfe, and another, had a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendencie over me, and I was, from them, to expect <hi>Orders,</hi> Ammunition, Proviſions, Armes, and all the Forces, which I was likely to have; and, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was left in my power, but the diſciplining of my Horſe, (of Foot, when I could get them) and the guarding of undefenſible, and bare <hi>walls,</hi> without <hi>works,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>ſtrong gates;</hi> which, to make the place more tenable, ought ſpeedily to have been looked unto, and provided for, in time; as might have been, and, as the opinion, which I then had of Sir <hi>Richard Onflow</hi> made me hope it ſhould be. But, after many meſſages, viſits, (and the keeping of <hi>Dawes,</hi> and <hi>Crowes,</hi> there, till I was aſhamed of my <hi>command</hi>) Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> himſelfe came unto mee, and, in ſtead of what I expected, perſwaded me to quit my <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> and to betake my ſelfe to my <hi>Troop</hi> only, as likely to be of longeſt continuance: For, (ſaid hee) though I procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you this <hi>command,</hi> for the preſent, and, to avovd ſurpriſall by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; it is not purpoſed, it ſhall be long held for a <hi>Garriſon;</hi> and, that if it ſhould be ſo continued, yet, I could not then command both. Vpon which overture, if (as perhaps was expected) I had perſwaded him, to aſſume the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon himſelfe, and, ſo complyed with him, that he might commendably have taken, thereby, occaſion alſo, to have ſo contrived it; I am perſwaded, I had, then, anſwered his expectation: But, I bluntly replyed to this effect: That I knew the place of ſuch concernment, as would make it of ill conſequence, if it were not ſpeedily fortified, and continued defenſible; that, to have the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of an <hi>Inland-Garriſon,</hi> without Horſe (an Enemie being in the field) was a kind of impriſonment; that, I, having taken upon mee the truſt, and profeſſion of a Souldier, it would be diſhonourable to mee, to give up the beſt part of my <hi>Command,</hi> to mine owne diſadvantage, without any ſecuritie, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164286:6"/>benefit to the Publike; and, that therefore, I would not aſſent thereunuo, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I ſaw no remedy: which, gave him ſo little contentment, that, with ſome faint promiſes of ſupply, he departed; and, never ſent mee any thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, but words, and diſcouragements; untill I, and my Troop, were called thence, to the undoing of the Countie, &amp; to the plundring of my eſtate, by leaving the Caſtle to the poſſeſſion of the Enemy: And, from that time till this, hee hath never been my friend, but ſometimes from the teeth outwards; and apparently injurious to me, oftentimes. Other reaſons I have, moving mee to beleeve what is afore ſaid, which I will omit till further occaſion.</p>
            <p>If the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard</hi> conceive, that ſuch thoughts, and ſuch a beleefe of him, as is afore expreſſed, are a wrong unto him; or, if it be injurious unto him, for me to think (as, I confeſſe, I do, upon vetie good grounds, in my opinion) that he is the greateſt Favourer of <hi>Delinquents,</hi> and the moſt bitter, and implacable Enemy to them, who are eminently <hi>Well-affected</hi> to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> of any man in <hi>Surrey,</hi> ſo much pretending the contrarie, as he hath done; Verily, he himſelfe, and not I, is cauſe of the injurie (if any be) by giving many occaſions of ſuch thoughts, and beleefe of him, as make it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for me, yea, and (as I heare) for many hundreds, to beleeve other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. It had been poſſible for me, to have concealed this <hi>beleefe,</hi> if his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, and the perpetuitie of his malice, had not neceſſitated an expreſſion thereof; as well, <hi>heretofore,</hi> for the <hi>Publike Securitie;</hi> as <hi>now,</hi> for my <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate vindication;</hi> and he had ſooner heard of it, but that wee knew not how to make approaches, for defence of the <hi>ſafetie,</hi> and <hi>priviledges</hi> belonging to the <hi>Whole Body of the Commonaltie,</hi> without endangering our ruine, by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to violate the Sanctuary of <hi>perſonall priviledges,</hi> though we did but break thorow their incroachments, to do our duties.</p>
            <p>Theſe particulars conſidered, Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow</hi> might have manifeſted more prudence, by forbearing, to provoke mee beyond all moderation; for, the patient creature, who can paſſe by ſcornes, and injuries, or let a Foole ride him, three or foure yeares together, without kicking, or hurling his Rider into dirt, may be pinched in ſuch a place, or <hi>Wither-gall'd</hi> in ſuch a hot ſeaſon, that his wronged patience may, perchance, turne into madneſſe, and ſo, both the Foole, and the Aſſe, miſchiefe each other. The heaving of me from the Seat of <hi>Magiſtracie,</hi> is not that which now moves mee to make this <hi>Vindication,</hi> though it occaſions it; but, the conſequences, which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, ſhould follow: For, I was once before put into authoritie, and out againe, ere I knew either the one, or the other; or, without ſo much as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or caring, who <hi>did</hi> it, or why it was <hi>done:</hi> For, I can be as merrie, and as wiſe, when I am out of authoritie, as when I am a <hi>Juſtice of the Peace;</hi> my <hi>Friends</hi> love me as well, my <hi>Companions</hi> think I am as good company, and (if I have not too high an opinion of mine own good diſpoſſition) the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who have taken ſo much paines, to put me out of their <hi>Fellowſhip,</hi> may have a worſe Companion, than I have hitherto been.</p>
            <p>For, I am not ſuch a <hi>Cynick,</hi> as manie, who know me not, have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed me to be; but, can ſit at a <hi>Seſſions,</hi> or <hi>Weekly-meeting,</hi> and heare ſome of my <hi>worſhipfull Aſſociates,</hi> make long ſpeeches, to the Countrey-people,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164286:7"/>without envying the wiſdome, which is attributed unto them, for it: and, whether they ſpeake <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or, <hi>non-ſence; impertinencies,</hi> or, <hi>to the purpoſe,</hi> it never much troubles me, ſo buſineſſes be timely diſpatched, and, our duties honeſtly performed, at the laſt. I could, alſo, verie contentedly, continue ſilent by them, upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> and permit them to have all the talk, and the mannaging of everie buſineſſe, without interruption; yea, and ſuffer them to reprove, or incourage, as there was cauſe; or, to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their own repute, without ſtriving to put in my word, or my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when it ſeemed needleſſe; except it were, that, the people might take notice of mee, and know mee to bee a man in authoritie, as well as they: And when the <hi>merit of the Cauſe,</hi> the furtherance of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or the prevention of an injurie, likely to befall any man, ſhall move mee to ſpeak, I love to do it, in as few words, as I can; that, they whoſe cuſtome it is, may have time to heare themſelves ſpeake, if any ſuch bee preſent. I hope (though I have heard ſo) there is no man among them ſo fooliſh, as to think me a diſparagement to the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> becauſe I have the title of a <hi>Poet;</hi> for, King <hi>Iames</hi> was ſo ambitious to be ſo called, that he preferred a <hi>Wreath of Lawrell</hi> (the <hi>Poets Crowne</hi>) before his <hi>Golden Diadem,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by ſome of his coines, and medalls: yea, that <hi>title,</hi> hath been, by the learned, reputed an honour, even to <hi>Salomon,</hi> and <hi>David;</hi> the tranſlation of whoſe holy <hi>Songs,</hi> and <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> by me, into <hi>Lyrick numbers,</hi> hath beene a means, ſo to ſanctifie my <hi>Poeſie,</hi> for divine uſes; that, this <hi>Faculty</hi> will not now render mee deſpicable, but among <hi>Barbarians;</hi> and, how they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of me, I care not.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lords,</hi> I perceive, this purſuit of my ſlipperie <hi>Iuſtice-ſhip,</hi> hath made my pen out-run the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> before I am aware: I will therfore, add a concluding daſh or two, and make an end. I doat not ſo upon ſitting upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> with Sir <hi>Richard Onſlow,</hi> as to be ſollicitous, for mine own ſake, whether I am in, or out of the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> for ever: But, for my <hi>Countrey-ſake,</hi> and for the preſervation of the <hi>Priviledges,</hi> due to a <hi>Free-Subject,</hi> I could not permit your candor, and credulitie, to be abuſed, by remaining miſ-informed; nor will my pen to be at reſt, untill I ſhall be fairly heard, to the repaire of my credit, (if any be loſt) and, to the repoſſeſſing of that reſpect which is due to a faithfull <hi>Officer:</hi> Nor will I be ſilent (if a patch of <hi>Freehold</hi> be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, that no worth or deſert is to be regarded without it) till I have, at leaſt, ſuch a proportion of my <hi>Loſſes, Diſburſements,</hi> and <hi>Arreares,</hi> paid unto me, as will buy me ſo much land of inheritance, as may make me a more conſiderable man in that <hi>Countie,</hi> where they have ſought to diſgrace me. No, nor will I then be ſilent, untill I ſee the Law, by which my <hi>Juſtice-ſhip</hi> is queſtioned, to be executed, or diſpenſed, equally, to all men, without partialitie; and, untill the election, and continuance, of all ſuch Officers, as are, or were, ordained for preſervation of <hi>Peace,</hi> the diſtribution, or execution of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and the <hi>ſafety</hi> of the <hi>Peoples</hi> lives, and Liberties, reduced to what (by <hi>Law,</hi> or <hi>equity</hi>) they ought to be.</p>
            <p>My hope, to ſee that effected, makes me indure, the more patiently, the <hi>ſcorne</hi> now caſt upon me, in requitall of all my loſſes, ſufferings, hazzards,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164286:7"/>and the forbearance of my Arrears. And, I doubt not but there will come a day, in which I ſhall not be thought ſo impertinent, as ſome of my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in <hi>Surrey,</hi> now think me to be: but, may perhaps (without fawning, or bribing for it) be thought as fit to <hi>ſerve</hi> in my own Countrey, in ſome place of profit, and credit, as to governe in the <hi>Summer-Iſlands,</hi> whither I ſhould have been ſent, laſt yeare, (and whither I would willingly have gone, if my loſſes, and arrears, might have been firſt obtained, to fit me for the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age) upon hope whereof, though that which is due to me for my <hi>Service,</hi> and by the <hi>Publike Faith,</hi> is enough (beſide my long forbearance thereof) to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe more then ten times ſo much land in anie Countie of this Kingdom, at this day, as a <hi>Iuſtice of Peace</hi> is required to have; And, though I cannot yet be diſpenſed withall, as well as my neighbours, I wil, nevertheleſſe, attend patiently, till that day of favour comes; and untill the <hi>Starres,</hi> both of the greater, and leſſer magnitudes, in our <hi>Engliſh Firmament,</hi> ſhall meet in a Conſtellation, which will be more favourable to me; and, make my inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable defects, as little liable to exceptions, as other mens.</p>
            <p>I perceive, many other, aſwell as my ſelfe, expoſed to ſuch uſages, who are wearie of complaining; or, who dare not complaine, leaſt they may be uſed worſe, by thoſe, who have the advantages of <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> openly, to illuſtrate their own praiſe, and, ſecretly, to diſparage other men. I ſee, daily, that they, who were generally reputed the moſt dangerous <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> and, who never ſhewed themſelves for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, (or, untill it began, evidently, to prevail) are, now, become power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full among us: yea, they are politikely ingratiated, indeered, and brought inſenſibly in, to ſtrengthen a <hi>Party</hi> againſt thoſe, who (from the beginning) have acted faithfully, and freely, for the publike; and, for the diſcoverie of their neutralitie, and diſ-affection, who, by now ſeeming to be <hi>with us,</hi> will more undo us, and more diſ-advantage the <hi>Common-ſafety,</hi> then all our <hi>open-Enemies;</hi> yea, and make our <hi>habitations</hi> unſecure, and our <hi>lives,</hi> for ever, miſerable unto us, if their combinations, and purpoſes, be not timely prevented, by ſome Ordinance, forbidding the admiſſion of anie ſuch to be in Authoritie. For, ſome of them are already in Surrey (as I hear) and elſwhere, in ſpight of the <hi>well-affected,</hi> made <hi>Committee-men, Commiſſioners of the Peace, Deputy-Lievtenants, Colonells, Captaines,</hi> and other Militarie Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, (I will not, yet, ſay <hi>Parliament-men,</hi> though I thinke I might) to the grievance, and oppreſſion of manie, who dare not ſeek <hi>Remedy</hi> leſt it prove worſe to them then the <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi> Inſomuch, that it is evident to me (and, as I believe, plain to manie thouſands) that, ſome have an intention, to diſcountenance, and diſgrace, by degrees, thoſe who have been eminently zealous, and freely bountifull of their blood, and eſtates, for the <hi>Common-liberty,</hi> and <hi>ſafety;</hi> and, are putting themſelves and their Confederates, into ſuch a poſture, as may probably, enable them, to continue the people in ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie to their pride, and arbitrarie pleaſure, when advantages may be ſecurely taken: which advantages, may, no way, be more ſafely gained, then by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe out of Authoritie, who have been a comfort to the <hi>well-affected</hi> from the beginning; and, placing in their ſtead, thoſe, who may diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164286:8"/>them, and incourage their malignant neighbours, as they do in <hi>Surrey,</hi> and elſwhere, alſo, as I am informed.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhips will, perhaps, think me <hi>tedious, over-bold,</hi> and ſomwhat <hi>impertinent,</hi> in this <hi>Apologie,</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrance;</hi> but, you would excuſe my <hi>tediouſneſſe,</hi> if you knew experimentally, how hard it is for a man to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, when he hath once gotten an opportunitie to ſpeake (of thoſe things which are grievous unto him) before Perſons, whom he thinks able to give him ſome eaſe; and, you will, I hope, pardon alſo, my <hi>bluntneſſe,</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,</hi> when you ſee (as in my Cauſe) what neare relations the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like-grievances,</hi> and the <hi>private-ſufferings</hi> of honeſt men, have one to another, juſtly occaſioning ſome tranſitions from <hi>private,</hi> to <hi>publike,</hi> and from <hi>publike,</hi> to <hi>private conſiderations,</hi> to the lengthening of diſcourſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our intentions.</p>
            <p>It may be thought, likewiſe, at firſt apprehenſion (&amp; to my diſavantage, if it be ſo taken) that, I have ſcandalized a <hi>Member</hi> of the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> by nominating Sir <hi>R. Onſlow,</hi> in this Apologie; but, I deſire it may be ſeriouſly conſidered, how eſſentiall it was unto my effectuall juſtification, that I ſhould nominate him; and, in what manner, and, with what circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances I have done it; for, I think it will then appeare, to the wiſdome of the reſt of the <hi>Members,</hi> that I have done my ſelfe right, without wronging <hi>Them,</hi> or <hi>Him:</hi> If it prove otherwiſe, I ſhall repent, and acknowledge my errour, with much contrition. For, I prefer the preſervation of their juſt <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> ſo far before mine owne <hi>reputation</hi> (though I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that before my <hi>life</hi>) that, I would expoſe my ſelfe to any hazard, rather than to proſecute mine owne vindication, by wilfull intrenching upon their <hi>Eſſentiall-Priviledges.</hi> And, I am perſwaded, I ſo well know, how to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between <hi>Scandalum datum,</hi> and <hi>Scandalum acceptum,</hi> that, I doubt not, but to make it evident (if it be any way queſtionable) that, I have kept within the <hi>Spheare</hi> of mine owne <hi>Priviledges;</hi> and, that it is poſſible, to purſue ſuch an Adverſarie, even to the <hi>Hornes of the Altar,</hi> and, yet, not pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the <hi>Sanctuarie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Common-wealth</hi> is more indangered by <hi>Mutes,</hi> then by <hi>Vowells;</hi> by <hi>Flatterers,</hi> then <hi>Free-ſpeakers;</hi> and more diſhonoured, by ſome of their owne <hi>Members,</hi> who are over-violently zealous for perſonall Priviledges, then by anie of thoſe, who, out of care, to preſerve the whole Body, may wring a part of it, for a while, by miſtake, or miſ-information. There was an <hi>Ananias</hi> among the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> without any diſparagement to the reſt; and as there have been <hi>Falſe-Brethren,</hi> among the <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo there may be, now, and hereafter, notwithſtanding any aſſurance we have to the contrarie. Therefore, to thoſe who are upright in the <hi>Houſes,</hi> and unto the whole <hi>Commen-wealth,</hi> we do more wrong, in being afraid to ſpeak freely, and plainly, of thoſe <hi>corruptions,</hi> and of thoſe <hi>Perſons,</hi> whom we think in our conſciences, may occaſion publike detriments and dangers, then we can do injurie, by diſcloſing of them, according to our <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>duty;</hi> though it ſhould be done with ſome indiſcretion, and circumſtances, to the diſparagement of a particular <hi>Member;</hi> ſeeing, it were better that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164286:8"/>
               <hi>one</hi> ſhould ſuffer, then, that, <hi>all</hi> ſhould be indangered, by our ſilence.</p>
            <p>This, is my judgement; and, my practice hath been accordingly, all my life; yet, I have not, either directly, or perſonally, charged any one hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; partly, becauſe, I apparently know manie things to be true, which I cannot prove legally, to other men: but, principally, becauſe, I love not to be an <hi>Accuſer of my brethren,</hi> or, a proſecutor of other mens infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, to their open perſonall ſuffering, ſo long as I may have hope to do it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, for their reformation, and without doing wrong, to the publike. But, if I find not the <hi>Inſolencies</hi> of ſome men to be ſpeedily reformed; and the good <hi>Affections, loſſes,</hi> and <hi>ſervices,</hi> of thoſe, who have <hi>borne,</hi> and <hi>forborne,</hi> for publike-reſpects, to be better repreſented to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (who, being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verburthened by the multiplicitie of emergent affaires, daily renewing, and preſſing upon them, cannot diſcover ſome things by ſitting in the Houſe, which we ſee, too often, by walking abroad) I ſhall be more particular in my reproofs hereafter, then I have been heretofore, whatever come on it: and, though I cannot, perhaps, deliver my ſelfe, from diſgrace, and that undoing, which my Adverſaries threaten; yet, I will periſh to ſome purpoſe (if I muſt periſh) by ſacrificing my endeavours (and life, if need be) for the reliefe of my <hi>Fellow-ſufferers,</hi> whoſe patience is almoſt quite loſt by their practices, who, by pretending to act with, and for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> doe ſecretly, and cunningly, what they can, to bring diſ-honour, and contempt thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by their hypocriſie, and injuſtice, which, I pray God to prevent: and, to let me live no longer, then I ſhall purpoſe, and endeavour (according to my underſtanding) to preſerve the power and reputation, of that <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court,</hi> in whatſoever I <hi>publiſh,</hi> or <hi>ſpeake;</hi> though ſome <hi>Members</hi> thereof, do, now, and may hereafter, forget their duties, as others have done heretofore; and, may thereby force me to expreſſe ſomewhat, for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of a <hi>corrupt-part,</hi> that the health and life, of the <hi>whole,</hi> may be preſerved.</p>
            <p>If, therefore, my <hi>Tongue,</hi> or my <hi>Pen,</hi> ſhall now, or, at any time, ſlip through indiſcretion, or frailtie, let me be conſidered, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie of my good intention, and the ſorrow which I ſhall expreſſe for my overſights: For, I deſire to preſerve a good opinion with your Honours, and, with all men, if it may be, in the performance of my duties; and, that thoſe, whom I love and honour, as I do your Lordſhips, and the two Houſes, (whereof you are Members) may not, at this time, be made Inſtruments of my diſparagement, without cauſe: Seeing, if my <hi>heart</hi> were as legible as my <hi>words,</hi> it would be no contentment unto you, that I ſhould be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced, before you had heard as well what might be ſpoken for mee, as againſt me; neither would you thinke it added any thing to your honour, if when your ſhort terme of <hi>Authority</hi> is expired. I ſhould be left in worſe repute, by your <hi>Act,</hi> then I was at the late renewing of your owne <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> But. <hi>Fiat voluntas Dei,</hi> I have diſcharged my conſcience, and, am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that <hi>God,</hi> who hath manie times heretofore delivered me from power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and malitious Enemies, to my reputation, and their ſhame, will be as mercifull unto mee, <hi>now,</hi> and <hi>hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEO. WITHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
